Prostitution Collection, 1834-1984
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Prostitution collection
1834-1984
MS 425
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Collection consists almost entirely of printed materials, also includes handbills, reports, speeches, trial transcripts, a Smith College course syllabus and unpublished paper, and an audiotape of The Dick Cavett Show on the legalization of prostitution. Focus on the United States and England, some items on Asia, Africa, and the Middle East.
The Prostitution Collection consists almost entirely of printed materials such as newspaper clippings, articles, and pamphlets dating from 1834 to 1984. Most of the material pertains to the United States and England, though a few items focus on Asia, Africa, and the Middle East. The nineteenth century material in this collection is limited, including the first annual report of the Female Benevolent Society of New York (1834); pamphlets on the "The Legislation of Female Slavery in England" by Annie Besant (1876) and "The Social Evil in Philadelphia" by Reverend Frank Goodchild (1896). Also included are two books on trafficking of young girls written in 1899 and 1910. The bulk of the collection dates from 1900 to 1978 and includes articles, handbills, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, reports, speeches, trial transcripts, a Smith College course syllabus and unpublished paper, and an audiotape of The Dick Cavett Show on the legalization of prostitution (1972). This material documents the changing relationships among prostitutes, the police, social and legal reformers, and the public over the course of this period. The impacts of the sexual revolution and the women's movement on attitudes about prostitution is particularly well-documented by the large number of newspaper clippings and articles from the 1960s and 1970s contained in the collection. This material sheds light on the lives and experiences of prostitutes.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additional Formats
This collection includes an audiotape.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this finding aid.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Prostitution--History--Sources; Prostitution--Laws and legislation; Butler, Josephine Elizabeth Grey, 1828-1906; Besant, Annie Wood, 1847-1933; Sophia Smith Collection
The Periodicals Collection includes several issues of Coyote Howls, "dedicated to exposing and eliminating current laws against prostitution."
- General, 1877-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
- Dick Cavett Show on the legalization of prostitution: audiotape, November 3, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- England (Box 1)
  - General, 1876-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Butler, Josephine (Box 1)
    - General, 1928-49, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Josephine Butler: Her Work and Principles and Their Meaning for the Twentieth Century by Millicent Fawcett and E.M. Turner, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Female Sexual Slavery and Economic Exploitation: Making Local and Global Connections: report of a consultation organized by the U.N. Non-Governmental Liaison Service, San Francisco, 25 Oct 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Organizations
  - General (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Association for Moral and Social Hygiene, London, circa 1927-55 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Female Benevolent Society of the City of New York: first annual report, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Smith College: student initiated course, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- United States vs. Corinne Smith; and United States vs. Demetria Moses: opinion, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bell, Ernest A. Fighting the Traffic in Young Girls, or War on the White Slave Trade, abridged version, 1910 (Box 2)
- Edholm, Charlton. Traffic in Girls and the Work of Rescue Missions, 1899 (Box 2)
- Greer, J. H., The Social Evil and the Remedy, undated (Box 2)
- Lowry, E.B. False Modesty That Protects Vice by Ignorance, 1914 (Box 2)
  - Millett, Kate. The Prostitution Papers: A Candid Dialogue, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Pankhurst, Christabel. The Great Scourge and How to End It, 1913 (Box 2)
  - She Wasn't Ashamed: The Autobiography of an Indian Prostitute, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Slade, Caroline. Sterile Sun, 1936 (Box 2)